<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 * ***********************************************************************************************
 *
 * Phoebius Framework
 *
 * **********************************************************************************************
 *
 * Copyright (c) 2009 Scand Ltd.
 *
 * All rights reserved.
 *
 *************************************************************************************************
-->

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "../../../../dtd/document.dtd">

<document>
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<chapters>
		<chapter>
			<p> Welcome to Phoebius framework developer manual! It is intended for everyone who
				wants to explore its rich feature set and develop object-oriented web applications
				rapidly. </p>
			<p> Phoebius is truly object-oriented full stack application framework that provides
				O/R mapping between PHP classes and RDBMS, defines infrastructure for
				the unification of application flow and ables to route incoming requests inside MVC
				stack. </p>
			<p> This manual covers various principles of the framework, functionality to implement
				the routines, and internal API that can be used to gracefully extend the existing
				functionality. </p>
		</chapter>

		<chapter title="Definitions">
			<p>
				<ul>
					<li><b>The framework</b> here is the complete distribution of Phoebius
						framework, which is located in a separate directory. This directory is
						usually called <code>$base</code> (base directory) for historical
						reasons.</li>
					<li><b>The application</b> here is a separate directory with the unified
						directory structure where Phoebius-based scripts (tied with a specific
						Phoebius distribution) reside. This directory is usually called
							<code>$app</code>. The application stub with the
						predefined directory structure can be taken from the <link
							to="/download.html">downloads section</link>.</li>
					<li><b>The front controller</b> is a PHP script which receives the incoming
						request and passes it to a Phoebius stack. In most cases, it is an
							<code>$app/www/index.php</code>.</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</chapter>

		<chapter title="Quickstart">
			<p> We've prepared a preconfigured sandbox where you can play around with Phoebius
				framework. Just download the <link to="/src/phoebius-app-latest.tar.gz">
					<code>phoebius-app</code></link>. You can also download the source code of the
					<link to="/src/phoebius-site-latest.tar.gz">
					<code>phoebius.org</code></link> website from the <link to="/download.html"
					>downloads section</link> - these are the best examples for the <link
					to="/support/a-beginners-guide.html">beginners' guide</link>. </p>
		</chapter>
	</chapters>
</document>
