<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
	* ***********************************************************************************************
	*
	* Phoebius Framework
	*
	* **********************************************************************************************
	*
	* Copyright (c) 2010 Scand Ltd.
	*
	* All rights reserved.
	*
	*************************************************************************************************
-->

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "../../../../dtd/document.dtd">

<document>
	<title>Defining a model</title>
	<chapters>
		<chapter title="Scope of this document">
			<p> This document covers the most important stage of the application development: how
				the project domain is defined, how its entities and their relations are mapped to
				the data source, and how they are used inside the application stack. </p>
		</chapter>

		<chapter title="Introduction">
			<p> Project domain definition is an important step towards the simplification of your
				application. When you describe the essences you should deal with you let Phoebius to
				handle a common business logic implicitly. </p>
			<p> This achieved simply as follows: <ul>
					<li> you create a project domain definition in XML using the packaged DTD (see
							<link
							to="http://git.phoebius.org/?p=phoebius.git;a=blob;f=share/Orm/Domain/Meta/Xml/abstract.dtd;hb=HEAD"
								><code>$base/share/Orm/Domain/Meta/Xml/abstract.dtd</code></link>); </li>
					<li> you ask Phoebius to generate a pure-PHP classes that represent the
						described entities and the database structure you need for a selected RDBMS
						simply by running a command; </li>
					<li> profit: a generated classes are the model you can easily use, apply and
						query within your application </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p> The simplicity is achieved using the unification of everything you should care
				about. </p>
			<p> Sounds simple, but this simplicity has a huge advantage of dealing with even huge
				graphs of entities without messing up the code. </p>
			<p> In this article you will learn how to define a mapping schema. </p>
		</chapter>

		<chapter title="Defining a project domain">
			<subchapter title="Basic definition">
				<p> When the requirements specs are written and analyzed, you may write down the
					definition of the project domain. For this purposes Phoebius provides a <link
						to="http://git.phoebius.org/?p=phoebius.git;a=blob;f=share/Orm/Domain/Meta/Xml/abstract.dtd;hb=HEAD"
							><code>DTD</code></link>. </p>
				<p> Imaging that requirements specification of a simple blog project defines the two
					essences: an <code>Author</code>, an <code>Entry</code> and a <code>Tag</code>.
					A relation between <code>Entry</code> and <code>Author</code> is
						<code>one-to-many</code>, and a relation between Entry and Tag is
						<code>many-to-many</code>. </p>
				<p> An <code>Author</code> essence has the following properties: <ul>
						<li><code>id</code> (type: <code>Integer</code>)</li>
						<li><code>name</code> (type: <code>String</code>)</li>
						<li><code>entries</code> (type: collection of <code>Entry</code> objects
							whose <code>author</code> property referes to the containing
								<code>Author</code> object)</li>
					</ul>
				</p>
				<p> An <code>Entry</code> essence has the following properties: <ul>
						<li><code>id</code> (type: <code>Integer</code>)</li>
						<li><code>title</code> (type: <code>String</code>)</li>
						<li><code>text</code> (type: <code>String</code>)</li>
						<li><code>author</code> (type: <code>Author</code>)</li>
						<li><code>tags</code> (type: collection of <code>Tag</code> assigned to the
							containing <code>Entry</code> object)</li>
					</ul>
				</p>
				<p> A <code>Tag</code> essence has the following properties: <ul>
						<li><code>id</code> (type: <code>Integer</code>)</li>
						<li><code>name</code> (type: <code>String</code>)</li>
						<li><code>entries</code> (type: collection of <code>Entry</code> assigned to
							the containing <code>Tag</code> object)</li>
					</ul>
				</p>
				<p> You may note, that we are currently not messing our heads with technical details
					of those relations: we do not specify any foreign key definitions, we do not
					introduce a proxy essence to provide a truly <code>many-to-many</code> relation
					between <code>Entry</code> and <code>Tag</code>), and we won't care about it in
					future because all this is transparently handled by Phoebius.</p>
				<p> Now lets define all this essences in XML format and put the definition to
						<code>$app/var/domain.xml</code>: <code-block title="$app/var/domain.xml"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE domain SYSTEM "../externals/phoebius/share/Orm/Domain/Meta/Xml/abstract.dtd">

<domain>
	<entities>
		<entity name="Author">
			<properties>
				<identifier />
				<property name="name" type="String" />
				<container name="entries" type="Entry" refs="author" />
			</properties>
		</entity> 
		<entity name="Entry">
			<properties>
				<identifier />
				<property name="title" type="String" />
				<property name="text" type="String" />
				<property name="author" type="Author" />
				<container name="tags" type="Tag" refs="EntryTag" />
			</properties>
		</entity> 
		<entity name="Tag">
			<properties>
				<identifier />
				<property name="name" type="String" />
				<container name="entries" type="Entry" refs="EntryTag" />
			</properties>
		</entity> 
	</entities>
</domain>
]]></code-block>
				</p>
				<p> You see that an XML definition has no technical details and describe essences in
					a human-readable language. That is a feature of Phoebius framework. </p>
				<p> Each essence has an identifier property, which is used with its default
					settings. By default it has an <code>id</code> name and is type of
						<code>Integer</code> (without specifying its size - a default database size
					of RDBMS will be used). </p>
				<p> Other properties, like <code>title</code>, <code>text</code> and
						<code>name</code> are scalar properties of primitive type
						<code>String</code>. </p>
				<p> A one-to-one relation between <code>Entry</code> and <code>Author</code> is
					defined by a <code>Entry.author</code> property with a type of
						<code>Author</code>. This simple definition tells us that an
						<code>Entry</code> has a property <code>author</code> which refers to a
					persistent entity <code>Author</code>. Internally, there will be a foreign key
					in a table that will store an <code>Entry</code> objects, that will refer to a
					primary key of a table that will store an <code>Author</code> objects. </p>
				<p> There are also virtual properties that describe <code>one-to-many</code> and
						<code>many-to-many</code> relations. These properties are called
					"containers" because they allow a developer to manipulate a set of referring
					objects. </p>
				<p> An <code>Author.entries</code> property is somehow a reverse side of
						<code>Entry.author</code> property and it represents a container of
						<code>Entry</code> objects that refer to a corresponding <code>Author</code>
					object. Such containers provide a wide API to manipulate the sets of referring
					objects: you may create, modify and drop the sets writing less codeю </p>
				<p> In case of defining a <code>one-to-many</code> association you set a name of a
					referring entity to a <code>type</code> attribute and a name of a referring
					property to a <code>refs</code> attribute. </p>
				<p> An <code>Entry.tags</code> and <code>Tag.entries</code> c simultaneously define
					a <code>many-to-many</code> association, but the difference to one-to-many
					association is that we use a desireble name of virtual proxy helper entity as a
					value for <code>refs</code> attribute: <code-block><![CDATA[
...
<container name="entries" type="Entry" refs="EntryTag" />
...
]]></code-block></p>
				<p> In this case Phoebius understands that <code>EntryTag</code> is not a property
					of an <code>Entry</code> object (and thus it is not a <code>one-to-many</code>
					association) but the name of an entity that should be generated implicitly and
					used as a bridge between two ends of <code>many-to-many</code> association. </p>
			</subchapter>

			<subchapter title="Defining an entity">
				<p> There are some ways you may customize the entity definition. </p>
				<p> When giving a name to a new entity, Phoebius automatically creates a name for
					the table to use for storing objects. By default it puts all the letters into a
					lower case prepending an unredscore to each uppercased character. For example, a
						<code>UserGroup</code> entity would be stored in a <code>user_group</code>
					table. </p>
				<p> When mapping an existing database schema to Phoebius, you may set a custom
					database table via the <code>db-table</code> attribute: <code-block><![CDATA[
...
<entity name="UserEntry" db-table="db_user_entry_tbl">
...
]]></code-block>
				</p>
				<p> An entity may also be non-persistant, i.e. it may have a class representation at
					logical level but without corresponding physical level representation (a
					database level) and thus cannot be stored or queried. A DDL for such entity
					won't be generated. To achieve this, just set <code>false</code> to
						<code>has-dao</code> attribute: <code-block><![CDATA[
...
<entity name="Primitive" has-dao="false">
...
]]></code-block> This technique is useful when you need to define a composite type for a complex
					property of another entity, or generate a class that will be helpful by itself.
				</p>
			</subchapter>
		</chapter>

		<chapter title="Defining properties">
			<subchapter>
				<p> Each property of an entity is defined in context of project domain, i.e. at the
					top of the physical level that used to store its value. A property definition
					contains a name, a type, the type options, value multiplicity, uniqueability,
					visibility and (optionally) the name of the columns in the database to be used
					for this property. A <code><![CDATA[<property>]]></code> node is used for that.
					Additionally, there is a special type of property called <code>identifier</code>
					and is represented by an <code><![CDATA[<identifier>]]></code> node: in
					addition, it accepts a <code>generated</code> option which tells the ORM that
					all new values are generated by the database. </p>
				<p> The most important feature of Phoebius ORM is complex mapping: any property can
					use multiple database columns internally. This achieved by a design of ORM type
					system: a property type itself is responsible for mapping database cells to any
					type or a class. </p>
				<p> A property value may have one of the following multiplicity:
						<code>zeroOrOne</code> and <code>exactlyOne</code>. If the property has
						<code>zeroOrOne</code> multiplicity then it may contain <code>NULL</code>;
					otherwise, <code>NULL</code> is not allowed. </p>
				<p> A property type defines how much columns it needs in a database to store mapped
					value. In that case Phoebius generates a corresponding DDL, prefixing the names
					of the columns with the name of a property. For example, if the property type
					requires two columns and you set it to a property named
						<code>localAddress</code>, then Phoebius will reserve
						<code>local_address_1</code> and <code>local_address_2</code> for this
					property. </p>
				<p> In case of tying Phoebius to an existing database, you may specify the database
					column names for each column explicitly, just be sure that you gave as much
					columns names as property needs: <code-block><![CDATA[
<property name="counter" type="Integer" db-columns="entity_counter" />
<property name="user" type="User" db-columns="entity_user_id_fk" /> 
<property name="address" type="LocalAddress" db-columns="entity_local_address_city entity_local_address_country" /> 
]]></code-block>
				</p>
			</subchapter>

			<subchapter title="Visibility">
				<p> An entity property may have one of the following visibility levels:
						<code>transparent</code>, <code>readonly</code> and <code>full</code>, </p>
				<p> A <code>transparent</code> visibility causes an Phoebius to hide getters and
					setters in an entity do not use it in a mapping. It is usefull when you want to
					define a column of the complex type in an XML definition and then present it in
					the generated DDL, but you don't want ORM to handle it, e.g.: <code-block><![CDATA[
<property name="childIds" column="child_ids" visibility="transparent" type="RawSqlType">
	<param name="definition" value="int8[]">
</property>
]]></code-block> This type looks complex to be handled by the ORM, but it will be presented in the
					DDL. </p>
				<p> A <code>readonly</code> visibility caused ORM to read the values of the property
					coming from the database and map them to the corresponding class, but ignore
					when flushing the values back to the database. It is extremely useful when
					dealing with database-generated values. For example, if one the columns is
					filled by an update trigger then it is important to forbid updating this
					property at logical level: <code-block><![CDATA[
<!-- an insert/update database trigger may recalculate the number of children automatically -->
<property name="childrenNumber" visibility="readonly" type="Integer" /> 
]]></code-block>
				</p>
				<p> And finally a <code>full</code> visibility is a normal and a default state of a
					property: all getters and setters are generated for it and ORM maps its values
					to and from the database. </p>
			</subchapter>
		</chapter>

		<chapter title="Property type system">
			<subchapter>
				<p> Phoebius provides a wide and extensible type system within O/R mapping level. A
					good architecture allows a developer to define properties of complex types whose
					values are stored in a multiple columns, it also allows to map values of any
					complexity to custom types and classes. </p>
				<p> Internally all this functionality is achieved by the descendants of <link
						to="/support/api/classOrmPropertyType.html"
						><code>OrmPropertyType</code></link> class - a property type handler, which
					encapsulates the auxiliary information: how much columns a property needs, how
					the values should be mapped, how the database value should be assembled to a
					class and how this class should be disassembled back to the raw database value. </p>
				<p> When you define a property of a some time, Phoebius smartly determines the
					actual property type handler to use. </p>
			</subchapter>


			<subchapter title="Primitive property types">
				<p> Primitive types represent native PHP values. They are treated as fundamental and
					thus used as the base for other property types. All these types are defined by
					the <link to="/support/api/classDBType.html">
						<code>DBType</code>
					</link> class constants. </p>
				<p> There are the following primitive types are presented: <ul>
						<li><code>boolean</code></li>
						<li>integers: <code>int16</code>, <code>int32</code> and
							<code>int64</code></li>
						<li>unsigned integers: <code>uint16</code>, <code>uint32</code> and
								<code>uint64</code></li>
						<li>floating-point: <code>currency</code>, <code>decimal</code> and
								<code>float</code></li>
						<li>string: <code>binary</code>, <code>char</code> and
							<code>varchar</code></li>
					</ul>
				</p>
				<p>To use them just set the value of the constant you need to use: <code-block
						title="$app/var/domain.xml" lang="xml"><![CDATA[
...
<property name="id" type="uint32" />
<property name="text" type="varchar" size="255" />
<property name="cost" type="currency" precision="12" scale="9" />
...
]]></code-block> Primitive types may be set with the predefined attributes that will be passed to
					the property handler: <ul>
						<li>
							<code>size</code> attribute defines the size of the type; it may be
							applied to <code>varchar</code>, <code>char</code> and
								<code>binary</code> primitive types </li>
						<li>
							<code>precision</code> and <code>scale</code> attributes may be applied
							to <code>currency</code>, <code>decimal</code> and <code>float</code>
							types </li>
					</ul>
				</p>

				<p> Internally Phoebius uses <link to="/support/api/classPrimitivePropertyType.html">
						<code>PrimitivePropertyType</code></link> to wrap a <link
						to="/support/api/classDBType.html">
						<code>DBType</code>
					</link> instance. </p>
			</subchapter>

			<subchapter title="Boxable property types">
				<p> Types can handle boxable primitives. This covers case when the native PHP value
					should be wrapped by the class which exposes various helper methods easing the
					usage of it. </p>
				<p> For instance, date and time may be presented as string, but when they are
					encapsulated in a class that exposes helper methods to work with date and time,
					then they become much more useful. For that purposes, Phoebius provides <link
						to="/support/api/classDate.html">
						<code>Date</code></link>, <link to="/support/api/classTime.html">
						<code>Time</code></link> and <link to="/support/api/classTimestamp.html">
						<code>Timestamp</code>
					</link> classes, that can wrap time, date and datetime string appropriately. </p>
				<p> To use a transparent mapping of a scalar to a box, you may specify the class
					which implements <link to="/support/api/interfaceIBoxable.html">
						<code>IBoxable</code>
					</link>. This interface provides a contract for explicit mapping. </p>
				<p> To use boxable primitve just set the name of the class as a property type - code
					generator would smartly resolve the actual property type: <code-block
						title="$app/var/domain.xml" lang="xml"><![CDATA[
...
<property name="created" type="Date" />
...
]]></code-block>. </p>
				<p> Phoebius will check if the specified type implements <link
						to="/support/api/interfaceIBoxable.html">
						<code>IBoxable</code>
					</link> and will use <link to="/support/api/classBoxablePropertyType.html">
						<code>BoxablePropertyType</code></link> if needed. </p>
				<p> The most important advantage of boxing is using an enumeration as a property
					type. When you define an enumeration (a descendant of <link
						to="/support/api/classEnumeration.html">
						<code>Enumeration</code></link>. If you define an enumeration which
					implements a <link to="/support/api/interfaceIBoxable.html"
							><code>IBoxable</code></link> interface then you can refer to this
					enumeration in property definition: <code-block><![CDATA[
class Color extends Enumeration implements IBoxable
{
	const RED = 'color_red';
	const WHITE = 'color_white';
	const BLACK = 'color_black';
	
	static function cast($value)
	{
		return new self ($value);
	}
}
]]></code-block></p>
				<p> The only limitation is that Phoebius reserves a varchar datatype for storing the
					enumeration value, so if you need to use a custom type then create your own
					property type handler. </p>
				<p> You may implement your own boxables too, just be sure that your new type can be
					casted to a scalar value without a data loss. </p>
			</subchapter>

			<subchapter title="Composite property types">
				<p> Phoebius framework v1.0.1 introduced a production-ready inline composite types.
					You are now able to define a property which points to a separate entity stored
					side-by-side with the property's entity, reusing a single database table. This
					is useful to propagate code reuse and moving the application code to the
					corresponding essences.</p>
				<p> The following part of <code>$app/var/domain.xml</code> defines two entities:
						<code-block lang="xml" title="$app/var/domain.xml"><![CDATA[
<entity name="Address" has-dao="false">
	<properties>
		<property name="countryCode" type="varchar" size="2" />
		<property name="city" type="String" />
		<property name="street" type="String" />
	</properties>
</entity>

<entity name="User" has-dao="true">
	<properties>
		<identifier />
		<property name="login" type="String" />
		<property name="address" type="Address" association="exactlyOne" />
	</properties>
</entity>		
]]></code-block>
				</p>
				<p> At the same time, Address entity is defined as storage-less: it is presented by
					a class, whose objects cannot be stored in the database
						(<code>has-dao="false"</code>). Therefore the declaration of a property
					which refers the Address type actually forces the ORM to expand the User's
					database table with the additional columns. </p>
				<p> Composite mapping provides a good abstraction and simple storage schema. You can
					refer the composite type properties without performance impact: <code-block
						lang="php"><![CDATA[

// get all users from the USA
$query = 
	User::query()
		->where(
			Expression::eq('address.countryCode', 'US')
		);

// acutally retrieve the list
$usaCitizens = $query->getList();

// dump it
foreach ($usaCitizens as $citizen) {
	echo $citizen->getLogin(), PHP_EOL;
}
]]></code-block> forces the following simple query to be executed: <code-block lang="php"><![CDATA[
SELECT
	user.login, user.address_country_code, user.address_city, user.address_street, user.group
FROM 
	user
WHERE 
	user.address_country_code = 'US'
]]></code-block>
				</p>
				<p> Of course, Phoebius allows you to nest composite types, query them and define
					multiple properties of the same composite type. </p>
				<p> Composite association has the following known limitations: <ul>
						<li>a composite value cannot of <code>zeroOrOne</code> multiplicity (i.e. a
							property that contains the object cannot be nullable)</li>
						<li> it cannot be referenced in a query: <code-block lang="php"><![CDATA[
$address = new Address;
$address->setCountryCode('US');

User::query()
	->where(
		// do not know what columns to use in condition!
		Expression::eq('address', $address) 
	);		
	]]></code-block> You need to specify the path to the final primitive property. </li>
					</ul>
				</p>
				<p>Nevertheless, it can help you in simplifying various tasks, providing a good code
					reuse across different components.</p>
				<p> Internally, a <link to="/support/api/classCompositePropertyType.html">
						<code>CompositePropertyType</code>
					</link> class is used. </p>
			</subchapter>

			<subchapter title="Associative property types">
				<p> Associative property types allow a property to refer to another entity by the
					identifier. In other words, it is a transparent implementation of the foreign
					keys in a way when you are working with a referred object rather than with its
					identifier.</p>
				<p> Consider the following example: <code-block lang="php"
						title="$app/var/domain.xml"><![CDATA[
...
<entity name="UserGroup" has-dao="true">
	<properties>
		<identifier />
		<property name="name" type="String" />
	</properties>
</entity>

<entity name="User" has-dao="true">
	<properties>
		<identifier />
		<property name="login" type="String" />
		<property name="group" type="UserGroup" association="zeroOrOne" />
	</properties>
</entity>		
...
]]></code-block>
				</p>
				<p>User and <code>UserGroup</code> are associated in <code>1:1</code>
					correspondence. In particular, this means that two database tables are defined,
					and the table for <code>User</code> entity contains a foreign key which refers
					to the <code>UserGroup</code> table and can be nullable (its association is
						<code>zeroOrOne</code>).</p>
				<p> Association mapping requires at least additional SQL query when assembling the
					entity: <code-block lang="php" title="assembling the entity"><![CDATA[
// two queries are executed implicitly:
// SELECT ... FROM "user" WHERE "user"."id". = 100
// SELECT ... FROM "user_group" WHERE "user_group"."id" = ...
$user = User::dao()->getEntityById(100);

var_dump($user->getGroup()->getId());
]]></code-block>
				</p>
				<p> This technique of cascade fetching may be avoided by setting another fetch
					strategy: <code-block lang="php" title="assembling the entity"><![CDATA[
User::dao()->setFetchStrategy(FetchStrategy::lazy());

// only one query is executed:
// SELECT ... FROM "user" WHERE "user"."id". = 100
$user = User::dao()->getEntityById(100);

// need to fetch a referred entity explicitly when using it
var_dump($user->getGroup()->fetch()->getId());
]]></code-block>
				</p>
				<p> In most cases, it is not needed because Phoebius uses an internal optimizations
					to send less queries to the database. For example. if you fetch a set of
						<code>User</code> objects (say, 100 objects) then Phoebius executes only 2
					queries rather than 100+1 queries (1 for <code>User</code> object and 100 for
					referred <code>UserGroup</code> objects): <code-block lang="php"
						title="assembling the entity"><![CDATA[
// SELECT ... FROM "user" WHERE "user"."id". = 100
// SELECT ... from "user_group" WHERE "user_group"."id" IN ( ... )
$user = User::dao()->getList()
]]></code-block>
				</p>

				<p> Internally, a <link to="/support/api/classAssociationPropertyType.html">
						<code>AssociationPropertyType</code></link> is used. </p>
			</subchapter>

			<subchapter title="Custom property types">
				<p> You may implement your own types easily if you need a complex mapping logic. </p>

				<p> Phoebius already provides a basis for you to avoid useless implementations. </p>
				<p> If you need to map a scalar type to a class (say, to wrap a value with a class),
					then <link to="/support/api/classBoxablePropertyType.html">
						<code>BoxablePropertyType</code>
					</link> is enough for do this. For example, if you need to work with date as an
					obeject, it is enough to create a corresponding class and implement <link
						to="/support/api/interfaceIBoxable.html"><code>IBoxable</code></link> as
					follows: <code-block><![CDATA[
class MyDate implements IBoxable
{
	private $dateAsString;
	
	static function case($value)
	{
		return new self ($value);
	}
	
	function __construct($value)
	{
		$this->dateAsString = $value;
	}
	
	function getValue()
	{
		return $this->dateAsString;
	}
	
	function __toString()
	{
		return $this->getValue();
	}
	
	... methods to handle date as string
]]></code-block>
				</p>

				<p>The property definition will like this: <code-block><![CDATA[
<property name="myDatePropertyName" type="MyDate" />
]]></code-block></p>

				<p> In such case <link to="/support/api/classDate.html"><code>Date</code></link>,
						<link to="/support/api/classTime.html"><code>Time</code></link>, <link
						to="/support/api/classTimestamp.html">
						<code>Timestamp</code></link> are implemented. </p>

				<p> By default, a plain string datatype is used to store the scalar value at the
					database side. </p>

				<p> In case when you need a custom implementation of the mapping and setting the
					datasource, you may create your own property type handler extending the <link
						to="/support/api/classOrmPropertyType.html"
						><code>OrmPropertyType</code></link>. A contract that <link
						to="/support/api/classOrmPropertyType.html"
						><code>OrmPropertyType</code></link> class defines is self-descriptive so
					its documentation should be enough to build your own composite type. </p>

				<p> Say, you need to define a custom type for a column that will store a
						<code>MyDate</code> value. Then you create a descendant, call it, say,
						<code>MyDatePropertyType</code> and type it with the class using the <link
						to="/support/api/classIOrmPropertyAssignable.html">
						<code>IOrmPropertyAssignable</code></link> interface: <code-block><![CDATA[
class MyDate implements IBoxable, IOrmPropertyAssignable
{
	// implementing IOrmPropertyAssignable
	static function getOrmPropertyType()
	{
		return new MyDatePropertyType;
	}
}
]]></code-block>
				</p>

				<p> All you need to know is that your <code>OrmPropertyType</code> descendants are
					not the classes that encapsulate a mapped value: <code>OrmPropertyType</code> is
					just an ORM layer workhorse which is responsible for mapping the database values
					to the business classes. </p>

				<p> In case when you need to make more abstract property type handler (that will
					implement mapping for various types depending on property definition), you may
					create a <link to="/support/api/classOrmPropertyType.html">
						<code>OrmPropertyType</code>
					</link> descendant, provide a public constructor and set the name of the type in
					the definition: <code-block><![CDATA[
class MyPropertyType extends OrmPropertyType 
{
	function __construct($typeParam1, $typeParam2)
	{
		...
	}
	
	... implementation of OrmPropertyType contract follows
}
]]></code-block>
				</p>
				<p>To refer this property type in a definition and pass the custom values to the
					constructor just use following example: <code-block><![CDATA[
<property name="property1" type="MyPropertyType">
	<param name="typeParam1" value="1">
	<param name="typeParam2" value="2">
</property>
]]></code-block></p>
			</subchapter>

			<subchapter title="Unique keys">
				<p> To make a property unique, you need to set the <code>unique</code> attribute
					value to <code>false</code>: <code-block><![CDATA[
<property name="color" type="Color" unique="true">
]]></code-block>
				</p>
				<p> As you define entities in context of project domain, you cannot create unique
					constraints over multiple properties, only a property value can be unique. </p>
				<p> On the other hand, you <i>may</i> define a composite property as unique: in that
					case, all columns that are used to store the composite type, will also be
					presented in a unique index: <code-block><![CDATA[
<entity name="Address" has-dao="false">
	<properties>
		<property name="countryCode" type="varchar" size="2" />
		<property name="city" type="String" />
		<property name="street" type="String" />
	</properties>
</entity>

<entity name="User" has-dao="true">
	<properties>
		<identifier />
		<property name="login" type="String" />
		<property name="address" type="Address" association="exactlyOne" unique="true" />
	</properties>
</entity>		
]]></code-block>
				</p>
				<p> Phoebius will generate DDL with the following unique index: <code-block><![CDATA[
UNIQUE INDEX "user_idx" ON ( "address_country_code", "address_city", "address_street" )
]]></code-block>
				</p>
			</subchapter>

		</chapter>

		<chapter title="Defining containers">
			<p> Phoebius allows generating virtual properties, that represent a sets of referring
				objects. </p>

			<p> When you define a container entity, then you get the ability to manipulate sets of
				those objects easily: fetch them, modify the set and drop it completely or by query.
				The actual database queries are generated transparently, and the dependencies needed
				to use table joins are resolved automatically. </p>

			<p> An API to handle sets is provided by <link to="/support/api/classContainer.html"
						><code>Container</code></link> class. </p>

			<subchapter title="One-to-many containers">
				<p/>

				<p> For example, if you have an entity <code>Entry</code> which refers to entity
						<code>Author</code> via an associative property type, then it is possible
					that you will have to write a query to grab a set of <code>Entry</code> objects
					that refer to a specific <code>Author</code> object. </p>
				<p> To simplify this task, there are container properties introduced. Say, the
					definition is the following: <code-block title="$app/var/domain.xml"><![CDATA[
<entity name="Author">
	<properties>
		<identifier />
		<property name="name" type="String" />
		<container name="entries" type="Entry" refs="author" />
	</properties>
</entity> 
<entity name="Entry">
	<properties>
		<identifier />
		<property name="title" type="String" />
		<property name="author" type="Author" />
	</properties>
</entity> 
]]></code-block>
				</p>
				<p> Please note that a container property defines a name of an referring entity and
					a name of its associative property. </p>
				<p> This allows to work with the set of referring objects as follows: <code-block><![CDATA[
$author = Author::dao()->getEntityById(100);

$entriesContainer = $author->getEntries();

// transparently execute: SELECT * FROM entry WHERE entry.author = 100
$entries = $entriesContainer->getList();

// transparently execute: DELETE FROM entry WHERE entry.author = 100
$entriesContainer->drop();
]]></code-block></p>
				<p> Containers are not mandatory and can be omitted in the definition. </p>
			</subchapter>

			<subchapter title="Many-to-many containers">
				<p> </p>
				<p> This association requires a helper entity to be defined, which holds the actual
					association between essences. You may define it explicitly as follows: <code-block><![CDATA[
<entity name="EntryTag">
	<properties>
		<property name="entry" type="Entry" />
		<property name="tag" type="Tag" />
	</properties>
</entity> 
]]></code-block>
				</p>
				<p> But Phoebius allows an implicit generation of helper </p>
			</subchapter>

		</chapter>

		<chapter title="Conclusion">
			<p> You've learn how to define a project domain and its entities, how to map them to an
				existing database, how to choose a appropriate property type and how to create your
				own property types. </p>
			<p> Now it is time to take a profit from this definition and generate the internal
				structures, classes and DDL over this definition using <link to="codegen.html">code
					generation tool</link>. </p>
		</chapter>

	</chapters>
</document>
